<?xml version="1.0"?>
<resume>
  <name>Stefan Karpinski</name>
  <email>stefan.karpinski@post.harvard.edu</email>
  <site>www.stefankarpinski.com</site>

  <section title="Work Experience">
    <entry>
      <name>Etsy Inc.</name>
      <link>http://stefankarpinski.etsy.com/</link>
      <dates>December 2009-present</dates>
      <location>Brooklyn, NY</location>
      <position>Data Scientist</position>
      <paragraph>
        <project>
          <name>Personalization</name>
          <date>2010-present</date>
          <description>
            Mathematical modeling of user taste, and personalized recommendations of shops and items across the website based on taste models.
            Design and deployment of systems required to implement these recommendations at scale, in real time.
          </description>
        </project>
        <project>
          <name>Analytics</name>
          <date>2010-present</date>
          <description>
            Design, development, and deployment of scalable systems to collect, aggregate, and analyze all events on site and events from internal systems, in near real time.
          </description>
        </project>
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Adtuitive Inc.</name>
      <link>http://www.adtuitive.com/</link>
      <dates>October 2009-December 2009</dates>
      <location>New York, NY</location>
      <position>Senior Researcher &amp; Developer</position>
      <paragraph>
        Built data scalable systems for processing and analyzing click-stream data using Hadoop, Cascading, JRuby, and Elastic MapReduce.
        Adtuitive was purchased by Etsy in December of 2009.
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Citrix Online</name>
      <link>http://www.citrixonline.com/</link>
      <dates>part time, 2004-2007</dates>
      <location>Santa Barbara, CA</location>
      <position>Networking Researcher</position>
      <paragraph>
        <project>
          <name>Network Path Selection</name>
          <date>2006-2007</date>
          <description>
            Invented and prototyped a completely redesigned Network Path Selection system, including the core prediction algorithm and data structures. This system provides real-time datacenter/ISP performance predictions for every client connecting to any Citrix Online service.
          </description>
        </project>
        <project>
          <name>Netmap</name>
          <date>2005</date>
          <description>
            Built a system to perform lightweight, real-time mapping of all Internet paths between data centers and client hosts, using probabilistic databases and information theory.
          </description>
        </project>
        <project>
          <name>Fast Failover</name>
          <date>2004</date>
          <description>
            Developed and prototyped a robust, scalable multipath route selection algorithm using a modified paired-series <italic>t</italic>-test. Also created a highly flexible Internet simulation environment for testing and evaluating multipath routing algorithms.
          </description>
        </project>
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>University of California at Santa Barbara</name>
      <link>http://www.cs.ucsb.edu/</link>
      <dates>2002-2004, 2006, 2009</dates>
      <location>Santa Barbara, CA</location>
      <position>Teaching Assistant</position>
      <paragraph>
        Taught weekly discussion sessions, held office hours, graded assignments and exams, created and maintained course web-pages, gave lectures when necessary. Subjects taught: formal languages and automata, complexity theory, advanced data structures and algorithms, software engineering, computer architecture, scalable web application development in Ruby on Rails on <link href="http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/">EC2</link> [<link href="http://courses.voneicken.com/ucsb-cs290f-fa06/index.php/Home">course website</link>; software used for this course became <link href="http://www.rightscale.com">RightScale.com</link>], and parallel scientific computing.
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Akamai Technologies</name>
      <link>http://www.akamai.com/</link>
      <dates>2000-2002</dates>
      <location>Cambridge, MA</location>
      <position>Software Engineer</position>
      <paragraph>
        Engineered, maintained and designed a variety of systems and tools for deploying, monitoring and managing Akamai's global content delivery network of 10,000+ servers worldwide. Primarily worked in C and Perl, with some C++, Python and Java.
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Harvard University</name>
      <link>http://www.harvard.edu/</link>
      <dates>1997-2000</dates>
      <location>Cambridge, MA</location>
      <position>Course Assistant</position>
      <paragraph>
        Taught weekly problem sessions, held office hours, graded assignments, created and maintained course web-pages. Subjects taught: single- and multi-variate calculus, differential equations, methods of numerical approximation, point-set topology, axiomatic and naive set theory, group theory.
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>The Rowland Institute for Technology</name>
      <link>http://www.rowland.org/</link>
      <dates>1998</dates>
      <location>Cambridge, MA</location>
      <position>Software Engineer</position>
      <paragraph>
        Designed and created a graphical, integrated suite of applications for Windows 95/98. The applications automate the control of equipment for cutting-edge research in quantum physics with scanning tunneling electron microscopes and allow on-the-fly graphical analysis of acquired data within a graphical user interface.
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Medical Liability Mutual Insurance Company</name>
      <link>http://www.mlmic.com/</link>
      <dates>summers 1996-1997</dates>
      <location>New York, NY</location>
      <position>Programmer &amp; Systems Administration Assistant</position>
      <paragraph>
        Wrote database query and information extraction programs in ALGOL, C, C++ and Perl. Worked in Windows, UNIX, Linux and mainframe environments. Assisted in network administration; installed and maintained PC hardware and software.
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
  </section>

  <section title="Education">
    <entry>
      <name>University of California, Santa Barbara</name>
      <link>http://www.cs.ucsb.edu/</link>
      <dates>2002-present (in absentia)</dates>
      <location>Santa Barbara, CA</location>
      <paragraph>
        PhD in Computer Science expected in 2010.
        Field of research: mathematical modeling and analysis of local area network traffic, especially using linear analysis techniques such as singular value decomposition, nonnegative matrix factorization, low-rank matrix completion, and linear subspace segmentation.
        Other major interests: parallel scientific computing, distributed systems, programming languages, computational theory, security and cryptography.
        Graduate studies include: algorithmic theory, distributed systems, modern programming languages and systems, automata-based complexity, networking, mobile and wireless computing, delay-tolerant networking, security, game theory, information theory, and stochastic processes.
        [GPA: 4.0]
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Harvard University</name>
      <link>http://www.harvard.edu/</link>
      <dates>1996-2000</dates>
      <location>Cambridge, MA</location>
      <paragraph>
        BA degree in Mathematics with honors received in June 2000. Harvard College Scholarship recipient. Have in-depth working knowledge of all branches of modern mathematics including analysis, geometry, abstract algebra, descriptive and classical set theory, point-set and algebraic topology. Course work in computer science included: network programming, mobile and wireless networking, mobile IP, routing protocols, natural language processing, compilers and interpreters, computational theory, tractability problems and algorithmic efficiency.
        [GPA: 3.56]
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Budapest Semesters in Mathematics</name>
      <link>http://www.stolaf.edu/depts/math/budapest</link>
      <dates>Spring 1999</dates>
      <location>Budapest, Hungary</location>
      <paragraph>
        Studied measure theory, integration theory (generalized Lebesgue integrals), Lie Algebras, functional analysis, Euclidean, hyperbolic and projective geometries with applications to computer graphics.
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <link>http://www.columbia.edu/</link>
      <dates>1994-1996</dates>
      <location>New York, NY</location>
      <paragraph>
        Audited courses in analysis and group theory.
      </paragraph>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <name>Regis High School</name>
      <link>http://www.regis-nyc.org/</link>
      <dates>1991-1996</dates>
      <location>New York, NY</location>
    </entry>
  </section>

  <section title="Skills, Interests &amp; Other">
    <paragraph label="Computers">
      Experienced using, administrating and programming for Linux, Mac OS X, and other UNIX systems. A thorough understanding of good programming practices and techniques, including test-driven development, agile programming, modularity, and object-orientation, allowing creation of more robust, maintainable code. Extensive experience with C, Ruby (and Rails), JRuby, Hadoop, Cascading, Cascading.JRuby (primary contributor), Elastic MapReduce, EC2 (and other Amazon web services), Perl, shell scripting, PostgreSQL, Mathematica, Matlab, R, LaTeX, GNU Make, and Git. Proficient in Java, C++, Python, Pascal, Tcl, MySQL, XML, XSLT, Apache, Javascript, ActionScript, HTML, CSS, Subversion, CVS, BitKeeper, and Perforce.</paragraph>
    <paragraph label="Languages">
      Fluent in English and Swedish; proficient in German and Latin; basic knowledge of French and Spanish.
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph label="Patents">
       The Fast Failover algorithm developed at Citrix Online in 2004 is patent pending at the USPTO [<link href="http://appft1.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;d=PG01&amp;p=1&amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsrchnum.html&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;s1=%2220080069104%22.PGNR.&amp;OS=DN/20080069104&amp;RS=DN/20080069104">Application 20080069104</link>].     </paragraph>
    <paragraph label="World Record">
      Fastest single-fare per-navigation of the New York City Subway system, riding trains stopping at each of the 468 stations in the system. New record time: 24 hours, 54 minutes, 3 seconds. Previous record: 26 hours, 21 minutes, 8 seconds. Co-holders: Bill Amarosa (Queens), Michael Boyle (Staten Island), Brian Brockmeyer (Brooklyn), Stefan Karpinski (Manhattan), Jason Laska (The Bronx), and Andrew Weir (New Jersey). We all went to high school together and completed the challenge to raise money for the school. [<link href="http://rapidtransitchallenge.com/">our website</link>].
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph label="Interests">
      Music of all varieties, reading, traveling, wine &amp; food, ultimate frisbee, learning languages, riding the subway.
    </paragraph>
  </section>

</resume>
